hello and welcome to the Greek Minds
series I'm super excited in this series
we have not one but two exceptional
guests I'm delighted to welcome our
first guest Professor Carl fristins a
leading neuroscientist known for his
groundbreaking work in brain Imaging and
his development of the free energy
principle on the other hand Dr Marcus
Mueller a physicist whose Academy
Journey step in theoretical physics and
Mathematics he's worked delve into the
Intriguing Crossroads of information
Theory and quantum mechanics today we
are stepping into the realm of
theoretical neuroscience and quantum
mechanics as we dive into the physics of
the first person perspective okay thanks
very much so let me say in advance
thanks so much for your interest and and
your patience your interest in all of
this
um let me begin with it with a
disclaimer so what I talk about today is
very speculative
um and probably to a large extent wrong
yeah it's also very abstract and
counter-intuitive so that's makes it a
bit challenging for me to to explain it
and to like depict what it has to say
what I can promise though is um that it
is a consistent approach it's I think
well motivated
um if it's true then it solves a couple
of interesting questions but if you
believe well I don't possibly think that
the world could be that crazy then
that's completely fine then you can just
see this like one hour of like fun
science fiction perhaps yeah
so indeed um
I'm usually working on other things also
some interesting overlap apps with
Professor for instance work on free
energy so in a very different context
um now what I'm talking about today is
in some sense a very concrete a concrete
proposal for a very different or unusual
picture of the world in which the first
person comes first in some sense
um but I should also say that this has
almost nothing to say about concrete
everyday questions like such as like how
concretely does the brain work right so
it's also not a you know Theory of
Everything or something like that
because it has nothing to say about most
physics questions that we're interested
in
um just to make this clear um here's a
comparison so suppose you're a proponent
of general relativity you know and then
you bring forward this very very popular
thought experiment of an observer in an
elevator
so this is for experimented if you're in
an elevator and you don't have Windows
to watch what's going on outside you
will never know whether you're floating
in outer space or whether you're free
falling on earth right
um now suppose that they bring you now
together in a podcast with a very
renowned biologist who's really an
expert on the biological details of how
the sense of balance works
then it may be quite hard for you and
the biologist to have a lot to say to it
say to say something to each other that
would benefit the specific questions
that that you're asking
um I I feel a bit similar so I feel like
I don't really have anything concrete to
say or directly to say about how the
brain works
um or what the neural correlates for
example of Consciousness are or
something like that
I also suspect that
um what I'm proposing the abstract core
of it is Manifest the indifference to
many of the specifics of how humans or
other instances of observers
um just happen to be composed and and
what they look like right like the
specifics of the world that we happen to
observe
nonetheless I I'm looking forward to
this discussion so perhaps there is some
common ground in the end I definitely
have to say that I found some of Carl
for instance ideas were interesting for
more unpopular scientific levels so
sometimes you know when I read on blogs
about trapped priors is explanations of
some psychiatric conditions also
explained with free energy principles
and I find this very interesting but it
doesn't directly touch my work
now I have three things to say basically
first is why should we have a thing like
this
how is it done in general and what does
it predict but before going there let me
ask back like
how much time I should take or whether
there are any any questions or comments
so far before I go to these questions
you should take as long as it as it uh
you you feel you need I for me I'm
looking forward to this this is going to
be a learning experience uh for me
um just a little just just to relax you
a little bit I I spent the weekend
reading about you I had to read the
proof of George's new book and he
clearly spent some time in conversation
with you I'm
looking forward to hearing the
um a summary of the ideas that you were
discussing with Georgia as I'm sure the
audience are so you take as long as you
want okay that's great thank you so much
um good so as I've had three questions
why how and what does it tell you so so
first why so what are the kinds of
problems that this approach tries to
solve
so
um consider the following question the
question is what happens to me next yeah
or what should I expect to see next
um now the goal of my Approach is to try
and give
and in principle answer to this
questions in all situations including
very exotic ones
so let me begin with a simple standard
situation like when I will ask what what
will I see next so suppose I go to the
laboratory here at at The Institute I
see a particular arrangement of mirrors
and of lasers and other equipment on on
the table
um and then what I can ask is well for
example should I expect to hear the
detector click
now certainly I can use physics in
particular quantum theory to compute a
prediction for example a probability of
hearing a detector click
so this is what we usually do in in
physics this is like the standard
methodology we say we remodel the world
or the relevant part of it and it's
Evolution then we locate ourselves
inside of it and then we calculate what
that kind of piece of matter is what's
happening to that right that's
essentially what we do even if we don't
spell it out always
um but then there are these exotic
situations where this prescription
doesn't quite work
um for example the computer simulation
of Agents so somebody promises to scan
you
um to whatever detail
um and simulate a copy on a computer for
example
um should you well what should you
expect should you expect to to make
observations that correspond to the
simulated agent or not and perhaps you
want to put a probability on that I
claim that physics is in principle
silent about this question
and then there are these duplication
scenarios put forward by philosophers
like parthit which are something like
these you know Star Trek science fiction
scenarios you enter this teleporter you
know you're you're dissolve and then a
copy gets built up on the planet where
you want to travel but then you may have
a malfunction and suddenly if two copies
appear or more than two copies with
slightly different properties how should
you think of that say before it happens
you know it will happen What should you
expect to happen to you like you know
um in physics in quantum theory in
particular there's a puzzle that
appeared that's called weakness friend
the weakness friend Paradox which
somewhat essentially asks how you should
think of being put in superposition and
whether what you predict to observe is
somewhat consistent with what other
agents might predict to observe
something
final example would be what's also
appeared in physics the the boltzmann
brain problem
I will explain this a bit more broadly
because I will pack it back to it
so this is in a nutshell so I apologize
to all the fellow cosmologists to know
this much better than me but the main
idea is very simple suppose the universe
is very large perhaps your model
predicts that
Eternal inflation or some other model
predicts that it's perhaps
combinatorially large
and then just due to thermodynamic
augmented fluctuations you know that a
lot of stuff must just go on randomly
out there
in particular in some of these models
you expect that there are many copies of
you just appear due to random chance
statistically
they would be perfect copies of you and
your memories but in the next moments
you know these
copies would somehow make a very strange
observations like what the hell is going
on and disappear yeah it's a very
colorful depiction
the cosmologists really want to think
about this because they might say well
if your model predicts that then maybe
your model is sick and you want to rule
it out
but again the question appears how
should you think of that in particular
if an observer in such a universe as we
think perhaps what should we expect in
the next moment to happen to you usual
Planet business or strange fluctuation
experience right it seems like in all
these cases the standard methodology
does not directly apply it's at least
unclear how to use it so you need
something else
so so that's the why now
um I think it's just a worthwhile goal
to try and have an approach that
attacks these questions uniformly and
says here's a method how you can in
principle work it out
good now how could you do it perhaps
um
so
um well how can you can you build now a
theory that would allow you to do this
there are several options yeah others
you know I'm not saying I found the only
one it's not even a full Theory but the
the main idea is when you say like if I
cannot apply this methodology
like here's the world it evolves here I
am
then gets one step back let's get one
step back
um and not talk about the world
let's let's first talk about you yeah
whatever makes you you so mathematically
you would want to say that something
like the Observer state
so that's whatever it is that is you
right now basically a snapshot perhaps
of
will not easily think of all the the
relevant content of your brain including
memories observations whatever will in
the end Define you
um we would think that perhaps
experience and Consciousness and all
that super beans on that somehow but
that's not necessary that's not
important for what I'm going to say
right so your state
doesn't have to be conscious or anything
so think of you during a surgery
it doesn't need to be human or
biological think of just some pattern
somewhere that causes what happens to
that thing let's talk about the Observer
state in itself
and let's postulate a law that says if
you are in that particular Observer
State now you will be subjectively in
another state next with some probability
yeah
um ideally that's it you just do that
you try to guess a well-motivated
probability law and then you work out
the consequences and compare it to what
what we observe
yeah now certainly what you want for
that to be successful with your demand
from this is that it should agree with
the physical predictions in the standard
situations at least in principle
even though it's maybe hard to apply in
practice
so you know you want to see the
situation where you go again to the
laboratory at The Institute with a
description of lasers and mirrors
and your state which includes all the
memory and whatnot things you're not
aware of that make up you you want to be
able to prove that this approach in
principle gives probabilistic
predictions that are consistent with
those that physics would give you
um if that's the case then you might
trust the approach enough to apply it
also in these exotic situations
that's that's the hope and that's the
that's the goal now you can ask well but
what could this probability law be what
would be a good choice and then I think
a good like well-motivated choice would
be to use something like a reverse
principle principle so it's like the
inverse of David Lewis principle
principle
and what it would say is that the the
actual chances that you postulate what
happens to you what are the
probabilities
um they they should coincide with the
epistemic predictions of maximally
rational predictors
so what does it mean like more
concretely well
um
I suppose I'm given you your state right
now yeah whatever it is
um I put it on the table I cannot really
do that but suppose I give it to a team
of scientists they are very well funded
they have all the time in the world and
they look at this string of data right
now
you can ask what what they unlike what
they could probably do is they could
work out that oh that looks a bit like
here looks like a recording of some
Digital Image maybe they there seems to
be a dump of the brain of some being in
a three-dimensional world and here it
can infer that stuff was moving in some
ways just from the recorded data you can
puzzle together a lot of facts about the
world where this came from and then you
can make a prediction and say well if
that's the case then this is what this
guy should see next
all right
um
so this is
um a version of universal induction
and to formalize that you can use
algorithmic information Theory so
algorithmic information theory is a part
of information theory that gives you
different options to formalize this in
in detail
what you end up with essentially say my
next state is more probable if it's more
compressible given the current one
so in some sense if the next statement
looks more business as usual or more
like a natural continuation of the
current one in a precise mathematical
sense
okay so that's that's the main idea what
you would want to to formalize yeah
um let me point out there are many
options how you could do it in detail
for example also how you choose how to
model Observer States mathematically and
so on right but it's also very simple
and you want to stick to it and not
postulate other things and see what
things it can
reproduce that we know about our world
so then if you do that then what so
there are questions what what does it
actually predict or explain perhaps
um one thing you get is automatically
essentially is you get consistency with
physics in principle
assuming that some version of the church
during thesis holds for our physical
world
the church during thesis will tell you
for example that if you build an
experiment
and you feed an exhaustive description
of the experiment into a computer the
computer can calculate probabilities of
future outcomes for you so there's an
algorithm in principle that can that you
can use to predict
if this is the case then you can prove
that in the long run the probability law
that I've told you will coincide with
the actual physical predictions
so that's consistency with with physics
um in this view however you are not
fundamentally actually embedded into
some physical world
instead the approach predicts that
in the long run U.S states will look as
if you were embedded into some larger
system
yeah that system is computable by a
short program on a probabilistic turing
machine
[Music]
and you can now call this your external
world if you want
so tells you that there exists this this
model where you can imagine that you
that you're part of that thing so what
the probabilities that you see are
marginal probabilities of this larger
process
and that would mechanistically explain
what you see so this is a sort of
emergent notion of an external world
importantly this is not a theory of
everything so a priori this approach
predicts almost no properties of that
world
except
that it's computable
that it's probabilistic and that has
probably simple laws even though the
actual realizations of the data you see
are probably complex
now this seems to be an agreement with
what we see but there's no claim that
this could actually give you the laws of
physics or you know it would be a theory
of everything of that sort now
at this point you might also understand
already how it how it solves the
boltzmann brain problem what what it has
to say about that
so again let me rephrase it quickly so
suppose this world around you that you
infer that you think sits there and you
know is consistent with the observations
suppose that has that property that it's
very large
and that you should expect that there
are many copies of you sitting around
now the first intuitive question is a
human that you want to ask is
now given all these copies am I the real
guy on this planet or am I one of the
copies yeah
that's what he would want to ask
intuitively
now now my Approach will tell you this
is not even a meaningful question
so there's no property of you that will
tell you one you're one and not the
others right you adjust your Observer
State your pattern right and that's the
same pattern here and in the in the
fluctuation out there
it's like the number six is just the
number six whether it's these six eggs
in the basket on my desk or the six
soccer balls in the room of my little
son
um however here's a second question that
you can ask and you can ask well good
maybe that doesn't make sense but
what should I expect in the next moment
to see should I expect to see business
as usual on Earth what I should expect
to see something strange that would
happen to these fluctuations
and then the answer would be this is yes
this is a meaningful question and you
should expect to see business as usual
continue
why is that well that would give you
observations that are more compressible
given your previous state
algorithmically
okay so this would also be bad news for
the cosmologists so in some sense huh
some cosmologists want to say hey fellow
cosmologists your model predicts so many
botsman brains then it must be wrong
because it's not consistent with our
observations
but in in my Approach
um you cannot do that right
um even if there are many copies the
sheer number of the copies would not
have any bearing on what you should
expect to happen to you and on the
chances of what will happen to you
finally
this is like the most counter-intuitive
aspect of it you do get an emergent
notion of objectivity
um and this is like the last thing
before I finish my long monologue
and it's perhaps the the most science
fiction and fun part
so
um
here's what happens to me right so I
I have these observations I'm in the
state and to me it looks very much if
there was this world around me and I can
point at something over there
um that thing or that that that seems to
to me like another Observer has yeah
carries a lot of data I would call this
professor Carl friston right
and so I can predict that
Tomorrow there's an almost hundred
percent chance that I will see Professor
friston see the sunrise right
so I can work out the probability that I
will see this other person see something
all I need for that are the laws of
physics I was like piece of matter that
records data does it like to the camera
eyes look at the sun yes or no
good now you can ask but what if you are
actually Professor friston right so if
you are that Observer State that's
represented in this data over there
um you can also like my Approach claims
that then you should believe your chance
of seeing the sun rise is just given by
this Universal induction probability by
algorithmic probability
and then you can prove a theorem that
these two probabilities are very close
to each other
as long as what I'm pointing to carries
enough information and is complex enough
so this will tell me that my world is
also Professor for instance world
and that appears also to other things
that are point to in my world even if
they are not biological like the data on
my hard drive for example or other
things that carry a lot of data about
the external world
it would not however apply to simpler
things
and then we would have the notion where
you know the the notion of objectivity
breaks down in some sense and you get
some something I call the probabilistic
zombie
so this would be situations where
me seeing something see something has a
different probability than that other
thing actually sees something and that's
totally counter-intuitive
and that's that's a noble like
phenomenon that's that's predicted by
approaches like mine
good so so that was kind of an uh a
summary of my proposal
um as I said it's it's not a full Theory
yet so I have the general idea and
perhaps you can see some of the ideas
worked out and explain how they should
work I have a concrete model worked out
something like a bit model where you
just model The Observer State as a
string of bits that grows one bit every
time that make a new observation
and there I can prove rigorously some of
the things I claimed
but certainly
actual observers forget something
sometimes fundamentally
so that's why
the rigorous version that I put forward
in this paper here certainly does not
apply yet
um and there's a lot to be tried and
improved and you may try out different
versions you might also try to falsify
it when you say here's statistical
predictions perhaps too strong
fluctuations expected on the laws of
physics we don't see them then we can
put the theory in the garbage can also
right so so that's also something to be
worked out
but yeah I'll stop here and thanks
thanks for for listening for such a long
time for your attention
love it doctor thank you very much that
was intriguing there's so much
um that one could pursue there
um I was intrigued by this notion of
probabilistic zombies so I I'm probably
gonna ask you to unpack that a little
bit more but
um just to celebrate points of contact
um you know I'm now pretending to be the
biologist who knows how the sense of
balance works and trying to try to make
sense of uh
your more
um fundamental and foundational physics
perspective but having said that a lot
of what you said
um makes entire sense
um when viewed through the lens of at
least a bio mathematician
um you know
um so I just wanted to sort of highlight
the points of contact which I understood
um as a Prelude to then going back and
looking at some of the more outrageous
um or counter-intuitive implications
of the way that you're actually
deploying this particular Theory
um so
a whole bunch of
um consilient observations
um that come from your formulation
um one way of reading your notion of
um the natural way to predict what will
happen next in terms of the
um the compressibility and the um the
minimization of algorithmic complex
complexity that that that is something
which
um I you know I can completely subscribe
to or when I say I uh somebody committed
to understanding things in terms of the
the free energy principle would
absolutely be there uh completely and
indeed there are I think two routes to
um motivating our understanding the
foundational role of or
um two roots to understanding processes
that look as if they're optimizing
something and the thing that they are
optimizing is some variational
bound on marginal likelihood or
um model evidence uh for me that would
be the variation of free energy and one
route would be some of the Richard
Feynman route uh from Quantum
electrodynamics and sort of thinking
about
um how you how material things things
like you and me
um from a biologist's point of view
um would actually make sense of their
sensory data in exactly the same way
that Richard Feynman was trying to work
out
um you know how he could make sense of
distributions of different small
particles pursuing different paths and
trying to you know derive the
probability distributions over those
paths which is an impossible
marginalization problem or integration
problem but can be sold by converting it
into an optimization problem so now if
I'm solving the same kind of inference
problems or perceptual measurement
problems or Observer problems then it
you know if I use that kind of trick I
will certainly look as though I'm
optimizing something which is bound on
the free energy and uh and that would be
I think the sort of um the the story or
the narrative
um that people like David McKay and
Jeffrey Hinton would use in terms of
appealing to uh
um that
that pathic reform formulation
um as the Genesis of free energy bounds
you know evidence lower backgrounds in
machine learning but there's another
route
um and I think it's probably one much
closer to your formulation which uh I
fondly think of as a Russian route so
the final would be the American route
but there's another that starts with
your algorithmic complexity and
formalograph and you know and provide
that right through so often induction
and Universal computation
um actually interestingly picked up by
people like David McKay
um in crypto analysis that that that
they're exactly the same
um maximization
of marginal likelihood and the
minimization of free energy
um sorry these things are exactly the
same as basically representing things in
a in a compressed fashion that minimize
the algorithmic complexity
um and interestingly
um if you look at uh
what current biologists are certain
neurobiologists like to think of as a
way of implementing this compression
um what it would look like in the brain
you'd end up with something called
predicted coding which you you know I'm
sure you're familiar with and of course
predictive coding was certainly in its
linear form was something that engineers
invented in the 1950s do compress sound
files to minimize algorithmic complexity
of the of of the encoding
of large sound files so to my mind
there's a wonderful sort of if you like
convergence on exactly the same quantity
and indeed people like Jurgen Smith
Hoover have been sort of you know
shouting about
um all you need is complexity
minimization to explain everything but
for for many many years now so I just
wanted to
um emphasize this notion that there is I
think a natural law out there that would
be under it by
um a compression uh a a a drive to
efficiency a probabilistic
um
um maximizing
the efficiency of something that you had
observed if if you that thing you
observed left its impression upon you
and your state you know that you were
describing all the states so constitute
me and my brain and all my internal
Dynamics
um then I think that you know the
argument that that natural law would
rest upon this you call it Universal
induction is that what you is that the
phrase that you used yes I used this
phrase yes yeah is that related to
Universal computation then is um as read
by your by the by the sort of people who
inherit from
um
either solemn off for indeed have you
come across the work of uh Wallace from
from Melbourne University
um in Australia uh so it is solomonov's
prior by the way I haven't come across
Wallace's work which which what's the
first name
I'm afraid I can't remember because he
was always referred to as Professor
Wallace but I do I remember visiting
Melbourne once
um and they had a philosophy slash maths
group
um that that
um and then so what Professor Wallace
was was basically the the head of
department and had died
um a few years prior to me visiting but
he was certainly outside Russia the real
champion of this sort of uh algorithmic
complexity view of um of stuff
self-organization through to you know
efficient coding through to Universal
computation and wrote some seminal
papers that they were very proud of so
so I I always try and reference this
gentleman professor professor I hope
I've got the name right I'll email you
afterwards um in relation to that
because you know I think that the
Australians felt they've been left out
of the the big arguments with the you
know the Canadians with with Jeffrey
Hinton and the like and the you know
some of the Americans and but I
just use him as another point of
reference that somebody you know outside
Russia saw this um as a your fundamental
way a universal way
um of understanding computational or
um you know
physics as computation or information
processing
um you know from the point of view of
com of complexity uh and just to bring
this point of contact to closure uh you
know that
um literally underwrites uh from the
point of view of crypto analysis uh the
kind of variational free energy that I
you know mean when I talk about
minimizing free energy
um when I when I think about this and
certainly an explanation to students
um
when taking a perspective on variational
free energy as an Evidence Bound in
statistics what I generally say is is
that you can just rewrite that marginal
likelihood or
um the variation of the energy in
physics would be the negative uh log of
that marginal likelihood as a linear
mixture of the accuracy and the
complexity where the complexity is a
callback Libra Divergence between your
prior and posterior so before and after
getting the observation
um the impression of that observation on
you your Observer State
um can be scored in continuous
formulations so this would be your
appropriate for sort of continuous State
space models as the KL Divergence
between
um the the prior and the posters are
literally scoring probabilistically the
degree to which that observation changed
your mind uh yeah you know that
fluctuation what you know what how is
how has it moved you from T to t plus
one and
um that's the complexity
um and of course because the log
evidence or the log marginal likelihood
is equal to accuracy minus complexity
if you're trying to maximize as an every
good statistician should the evidence
for her hypotheses
um then you are going to try to maximize
the accuracy of your account of this
observation but under the conclusional
constraint you're trying to minimize the
complexity
uh and it is that link I think which is
fundamental and sort of ties you to the
universal induction and Universal
computation that's the compression so
you don't want to change your mind too
much because every you know if you
change your mind and use up degrees of
freedom you're now incurring a
complexity cost which is exactly uh what
you don't want to do so I normally read
that sort of Occam's razor aspect
um which I think you could also read in
terms of James's maximum entry principle
um or even Jeffrey's prize and
statistics I I read that as basically
um get it getting the right priors to
enabling you to compress everything so
you don't need to move away from your
prize if you can compress this
information and understand it and
rewrite it or explain it in terms of
good prize you've already got then your
posterior doesn't move very much and
you've now got the most efficient
compressed representation I I'm not not
sure about the maths and I'm sure you'll
be much more fluent in this than I am I
remember looking at into it once and
trying to use the law of large numbers
to connect this
um statistical measure complexity to the
algorithmic complexity but at least
heuristically I I just look at these
things as just two ways of looking at
the same phenomena one from the point of
view of continuous State spaces and one
from the point of view of sort of you
know discrete bits or you know of
a kind that you could apply algorithmic
complexity to
have you come across that sort of
statistical complexity thing before the
uh yes yes indeed so I'm glad you you
say this
um so certainly a lot of what you say is
corroborated by a couple of theorems
that relate for example chronograph
complexity and entropy or you know um
conditional comographer of complexity
and coolback Library Divergence
so essentially the expected value of
chronograph complexity is entropy
um so this is why you intuition that you
mentioned like you know how surprised Am
I by the new observation giving the
previous one is mentioned by the
Callback Library Divergence can be
interpreted as some kind of expectation
of a conditional algorithmic
um complexity except certainly that
you're in the continuous regime no so
um what I said is true for the for the
discrete one but but surely this
connection can be made
and
this is something I I definitely find
interesting because I'm indeed looking
at alternative ways to model Observer
States right to model probability
distribution
um in particular ones where I don't have
to add a bit at a time
I know I wonder whether I should you
know study in more detail how you
actually formalized it
um I haven't enough right but yeah go
ahead well yeah I would certainly
encourage you to do that because um it
is seldom the case that I meet somebody
who is uh fluent in both the continuous
sort of
um uh
um data analysis kind of computational
complexity and the you know the inherent
information geometries and continuous
State spaces I think you know things
like
um
um vicious information uh metrics and
information geometry and you know how
that relates and how thinking about this
sort of
um complexity measure as a KL Divergence
moving from your post device to from
your prior to your poster is literally a
movement on a statistical manifold that
has an informational lens that whose
metric is efficient information so the
whole bunch of beautiful maths but it's
all in continuous State spaces
I if if you could understand and become
fluent in that to the extent you could
join the dots with the with the pure
algorithmic stuff I think that would be
a great service I'm sure these are
exactly the same stories written in a
slightly different rhetoric from the
point of view of different kind of
mechanics
um uh you know and I'm not sufficiently
well versed in the algorithmic uh
complexity and Universal computation to
really sort of say these are are
basically the same kind of story if you
could do that I think that would be uh
would be you know you're very very
useful and you you'd make a lot of
threads or at least allow people to to
see each other's perspective so I just I
I just really encourage that if you know
if it can be done and don't forget to
cite this this Australian gentleman
Wallace
is it
Professor is it Chris or Mark that is
two one of it is called Chris uh
Chris Wallace
is into information science is that
could be him
uh that doesn't mean he used to be it um
I'm pretty sure it's Monash University
in uh Melbourne in uh it's Mark Wallace
I think Mark Wallace it's Mark Wallace
yeah right yeah and you know he
he would have been writing I think in
the in the sort of uh 80s and late 90s
if I remember correctly so I'll do my
research I'll send you my favorite
citations that
sort of captured the essence of this you
know the things that we've been talking
about
but that is really interesting and I
thank you so much for pointing me to
this I do have a somewhat question for
you of technical curiosity so
um are there results that say something
like if the environment if the world is
of that on that kind then I obtain a
guarantee
um that the free energy minimization
will be successful for survival for
example
so I guess
so for algorithmic complexity for
example it would be a version of church
during thesis so you need some in
principle computability
but probably you would also be able to
say something about
um for the statistical version like
probably the environment shouldn't be
too unpredictable in principle or
something like this
I see um
yes I I'm afraid that there isn't you
know well
um and I'm probably not the best person
to ask I mean basically you know because
my background is more sort of intuitive
physics and and yes mathematics but um
there
are certainly
um a lot of Notions that would speak to
that
um that basic outcome that if you are um
embedded uh in some meaningful way but
individuated from
um a particular environment external
media some some Niche
um then there would have to be
um a non-equilibrium steady state
exchange
um between you and the Observer uh and
the thing generating observations I know
you may not like that because your
health thesis isn't there's nothing
generating observations in my world but
with slightly less uh less philosophical
about it you you assume that there is
there is some World there and you've got
some um Observer uh and they are
individuated in some well-defined sense
so that um the observations that are
doing the updating and the updating is
in the direction of
um being maximally compressible or
minimally complex uh under the
constraint of it's still providing a a
good representation or accurate
explanation for
um
um just Open brackets you know if you
could show the equivalence you've also
now got a a con a duality with James's
maximum entry principle if you read the
maximum entropy about of the
probabilistic description of what caused
your measurement your observation so
that you know the constraint just is um
well one way of reading this is that the
constraint
um is supplied by or at least scored by
the accuracy of
um you know of of your measurements it's
you'd have to move certain terms around
um but put simply you know the free
energy formalism can also be read
allergens in the sentence that you've
got an entropy of some belief
distribution encoded by your Observer
States
um that um has to be maximized in the
spirit of Occam's razor you don't want
to commit to a particular explanation so
it has to be simple in the sense it has
to be liberal and non-committal but
you've got a constraint and that
constraint can be written down in terms
of lagrangians or LaGrange multiplies or
uh or specifically in the for the point
of view of the free energy principle
um a um
a log a negative log probability
um of particular observations and indeed
the other the the external States
causing them
um sorry I'm
just I'm just uh adding a little bit of
momentum to my
um and uh encouragement to you to to
actually you know join all of these dots
because if you can join it to the free
energy principle the statistical you
know the basis statistician's use of of
um uh variational
um free energy as a you know as an
objective function to get good models of
things to make sense in the best kind of
way of observations you've also got an
easy
um point of connection with um with um
Max eventually maximum caliper uh um
principles from James as well so you
could tie it everything together but
sorry to come back to your question the
um
so in that respect
um then you can
um in fact the answer to your question
really is the the
um
the the race on Tetra or the free energy
principle that if you have um a system
that is um in some characteristic States
on that system so the Observer can be
separated from the thing that's
providing the observations then just by
the existence either of a
non-equilibrium steady state an open
exchange so these are all about open
systems then
um just by either the existence of that
non-equilibrium satisfied solution or
the existence of uh Dynamics
um at any you know for a suitably long
period of time then you can always
um explain the change in the state of
the Observer
um in continuous State space
formulations as a gradient flow on the
the other the the variation for energy
that has this complexity uh
computational complexity
part of it so the answer is yes possibly
their way around if you are in
non-equilibrium steady state exchange
with your environment
um another way of reading that would be
you know if you
um add events some kind of generalized
synchronization of chaos if you want to
put some random fluctuations in in play
then there will always be a description
of your next state or your current
Dynamics as a gradient flow on the same
quantity that hopefully we share a
commitment to uh that has this sort of
compression uh compressibility aspect to
its efficiency aspect uh to it
um so that's certainly true uh early
versions of that
um
which you know would be another nice
thing to sort of draw into the fold of
things that that are all if you like um
pointing the same direction inheritance
on cybernetic so this is the work of
people like Ross Ashby
um and Colin um so things like the good
regulator theorem and the law of
requisite variety could in one sense be
read as answers to your question so uh
have you come across those those early
Notions no I'm not at all familiar with
this oh you'd like that
um and he also
um was able to prove stuff I never
really I had I tried to read the papers
I never really understood the proofs
um but yeah I think you would like this
so that this is um this is Circa uh you
know probably
um 1950s possibly later 70s um but
um but certainly the early work of
people like Ross Ashby
um so the good regulator theorem just
says that any Observer
that it lives in a controllable world
must be a model of that world
um so and the law of requisite variety
can also be read as the degrees of
freedom of the Observer the observer's
state
must be at least those
um or have a cardinality of the
environment that is being controlled so
again this notion of being and it's a
notion I think was implicit in your
opening comments about you know where
should I look next so it's all about
actively controlling not controlling but
engaging with a world so you're open to
something that you're observing so you
can control your observations by where
do I look over here over there so from
the point of view of the good regulator
theorem
um is assuming or they were assuming
um that there is an observer
um there are things out there that could
be controlled you know you know the
Observer doesn't know you don't
necessarily need to know the structure
of what those things are there just
needs to have enough degrees of freedom
on the inside the internal bulk
um to match the you know those things
that can be controlled out there and
then it is provingly the case that if
you have the open exchange with
the world then the internal
um the internal Dynamics The Observer
states must be readable as or be a good
model of the uh of what's going on out
there and it may be that the proofs do
actually
um sort of your portend the later
derivations
um that you know eventually several
decades later led to the universal
computation and as I understand it
Universal Universal induction
um but you'd have to go back to the yeah
I think to that very early literature
um so that would be one other way of
saying that yo if I exist in a world and
I can observe that world under the
caveat I have to uh control the
um the way that I solicit those
observations I have to actually you know
have some reciprocal
exchange with that world then yes the
you know there can be no other solution
to that than me being a good model of
that world of course what is being a
good model mean well it means I've got a
compressed representation of the causes
of my Sensations and what does that mean
if I'm
um if you're in Universal time well it
just means that my States will be those
that maximize the model evidence in a
continuous formulation not some model
evidence it's exactly what we're saying
before it's a thing that's bounded it is
just the mixture of the accuracy and and
the complexity so I think it all it all
does fit together
um I know I repeat it will be
interesting if I remember if I remember
the proofs of the co-regulator theorem
um although they may be a little bit
heuristic from for your tastes given you
know the formalisms that ensued they may
have been articulated in the kind of
language which which you you you would
recognize I said it's an elemental
umesque information theoretic um
yes indeed I'm actually intrigued by a
description I should say
um in many cases what I used are
theorems that as theorems can be read
either way so that could be applied like
thought of being applied in situations
where I think of an observer that is
actually embedded in a fundamental way
or use the theorem and turn it around
and use it in my Approach so to get one
step back I'm just interested in in this
for like what you can prove that in
generality and what he said intrigued me
because this could regulator theorem
when you say well the Observer has to
have enough degrees of freedom for the
world somehow The Observer states must
contain a good model for the world in
order to have the ensuing sustainability
of that Observer that's mathematically
really similar to my condition for not
being a probabilistic zombie Ah that's
essentially the same condition so the
Observer state must contain enough
information about the part of the
external world that affects affects them
and if so then it's not a probabilistic
zombie and then the probabilistic
predictions that you would put forward
if you just describe that world would
match the probabilistic predictions that
you would get if you applied it directly
to your server state so I'm intrigued by
these proposals because they seem
disappointed some very deep mathematical
underpinnings that perhaps can then also
be used to make a more conceptual
relation to this
um more statistical approach that you're
working with I definitely want to pursue
this so I thank you already for for
pointing me to this
and we've happily got back to the
probabilistic zombies so that's that was
a big clear can you just speak more
about the problem that was intriguing
the probabilistic zombie
yes
um so
so in my Approach the notion of
objective reality is not assumed and
built into the formalism as you would
typically do but it's it's the content
of a theorem that you prove right
um and certainly every theorem has its
premises and it isn't that premises you
get that conclusion
and the the premise of of this theorem
is has to do with
that other thing that you're pointing
though that the interpret as another
Observer containing enough information
about your world
um right so you can quantify this in
terms of chronograph complexity
essentially
um and of the world I really mean
essentially the laws and not the actual
realization
so
um somehow when when you
when I pointed your brain and I I'm I
think that we we have objective
descriptions or what I think my
probabilistic predictions are for what
happens to you should agree with yours
then this has to do with in my Approach
with saying well the comogra of
complexity of your state
[Music]
um
over this is much larger essentially
even the comograph complexity of of the
laws of the worlds that affect you at
the regime where you live just the laws
not the actual data of the air molecules
or so that would be a high complexity
but the laws by which they move
essentially
um so intuitively
I would say that this applies to you
know certainly all other things we would
intuitively call Observers
it doesn't apply to
um things that are point to that have
very slow small information content
and it also applies in situations where
so how should I say
um
so like computer simulation of Agents
so
you can simulate a simulated being in a
simulated world on a computer
um may have large information about its
simulated world but not about ours about
our world yeah that's why in my Approach
essentially it's the simulated world
that's effective for that simulated
being right and so for example if you if
you depict that simulated being in a
world where beings just happen to suffer
then you shouldn't feel guilty because
you're not causing that that's
a bit the idea but as soon as you start
talking to the simulated being like and
you feed and some data and say look
you're actually a simulation here's some
photographs of our galaxies and that's
what our laws look like and so on
then you would at some point overwhelm
its Observer state with enough
information about our outside world so
that whatever
we decide to do in our world becomes
causally effective for its subjective
transitions
and then you put should feel guilty at
some point yeah so I'm very awake and
quick here and it sounds a bit crazy but
that's somewhat the predictions that you
get right
um so probabilistic zombie again to
summarize would be a thing
where it would have different
probabilities
when you were that thing as compared to
how I would see that thing it will this
would be different probabilities
[Music]
and that's counter-intuitive because I
think that
even in in thought experience like you
think of like the many worlds
interpretation of quantum mechanics or
other extreme situations that you think
of we typically don't think about it in
that along these lines so because that
would be a bit strange
[Music]
um
maybe to finish this one one other
thought experiment
um that had with George muscle recently
so we had a couple of emails exchanged
and
um I I tried to explain the main idea
but not sure how well it went
um it's a bit the idea again of computer
simulation so
um in the future you know you run you
you buy a lot of computing time and then
you simulate on your computer simulated
Universe right according to simple laws
you have lots of compute so you know you
have like Evolution starting and yes and
you have a in your simulation and some
evolved being comes up and asks about
the meaning of it all and what's going
on and
you know finds perhaps by
experimentation the laws of its
simulated world
and now you go ahead and say well you
intervene in the simulation you change
its laws immediately yeah
perhaps you know you change something
dramatically that's kind of on the sky
far away from the simulated being
and then at some point that simulated
person wakes up and sees in the
newspapers that NASA does like
astronomers can't believe it suddenly
the sky has changed and some regime of
the universe what the hell is going on
right now
that would have a very strange
description and approach like mine
because in my Approach you can think
about the simulated being before reading
the newspaper just as long as the
simulation is going as usual according
to its laws
they would say well fair enough you know
if you were that simulated being
then what you would see is also what we
as from from the outside would see right
so you and your simulation you will see
the simulated sunrise and if you rather
simulate like that Observer State that's
represented by a simulation you would
actually also see the sunrise
but at that moment when you change the
laws drastically these probabilities
would diverge if you were that Observer
state that was simulated you would
probably see
um
the the old laws just continue
right
so whereas you looking at your
simulation where you intervened you
would observe a simulated being with
high probability that has actually
experienced the change of laws and seen
that
so so one very colorful intuitive way to
interpret this would be to say well
somehow somehow
the the person has leaked out of the
simulation
that has been replaced by a kind of
unlikely change link somehow
um no no you have this this other thing
that you simulated and you can ask about
what would it be like to be that thing
right but that would be somewhat a
separate question of asking it for this
Observer State before the change so
you'd have these very strange and very
counting to the phenomena of kind of you
know persons falling out of it the
universes also like which
are hard to to visualize I think
yeah but it wouldn't happen to you and
me because we're not probabilistic
zombies relative to each other well
yeah but I mean of course you know with
all the current
um excitement about large language
models and giant AI I mean in terms of
AI alignment and the ethics of um having
large generative models say generative
AI in silico uh I think you know I'm
just wondering whether some of these
arguments are actually practically and
morally uh you're in a philosophical
sense uh you know
um quite
prescient you know given current sort of
focus on say regulation you know how how
expressive how big can these charity AIS
come
um and to what extent does their
training correspond to perceiving
receiving observations and trying to
make sense of those in a base optimal
way using using the principles of
universal computation and of course this
is all in Silicon usually on a van
Newman architecture so I do think that
there is practically possible the
possibility of these probabilistic
zombies where there's a there's you know
perhaps I should rephrase what I have in
mind
um from from respect from my perspective
um as
um a modeler and a modeler of modelers
you know I.E other people
um so you know I can certainly describe
my brain or indeed um my family
um in terms of uh it looks as if they
are
um maximizing the evidence for the for
the models of their sensed World
um
and then I can try and create a little
artifact a little synthetic person and
we do this quite a lot in a very very
um Elemental way just you know just to
simulate toy games and you know
economics games and psychophysics
experiments with the aim of trying to
fiddle with the parameters usually of
the prior beliefs of of The Observers uh
you know you talk about the laws and the
contingencies that are normally written
in down in terms of tries in terms of
generative models and we build these
little synthetic
um agents to adjust the prize until
their response to an experimental
Paradigm matches that of a patient or a
subject just to try and get a it's like
a digital twin in the computer which you
can then now start to ask what would
happen if I gave them this synthetic
drug or change this connection
um or to try and understand the uh the
sense making implicit in these so you
know there that there is a your very
practical
um if you like
um instance of probabilistic zombies
that people are actually using in
computational neural Psychiatry for
example uh actually at hand as you can
see the your
um another interesting example of this
is the virtual brain project
um that's come and deal you spin the
auspices of the human brain project and
now e-brains
um and the whole point of that is is to
create digital twins of people with
epilepsy
so that you can ask well if I did this
surgery to relieve this intractable
epilepsy what would happen before you
actually do it on the actual patient so
you know there are people out there
building zombies
and the reason they're probabilistic
zombies perhaps not the virtual brand
because that just tries to reproduce
neuronal like biophysical Dynamics but
but some of the uh agents that we build
actually aren't that they actually are
with stall in them generative models
prior beliefs of A probabilistic
Sort that provide the constraints we
were talking about before
um the other underwrites their
constrained maximum entry principle
um
so that we are unlike me trying to
describe a member of my family so I can
see how my family the member of my
family behaves I can look at the
Dynamics and I can reverse engineer like
kind of model Observer model that that
was
um if you're like underwriting their
Dynamics you know from your point of
view that uh you know Universal
induction being an expression of some
lipunoff function for you it could be
sort of you know an algorithmic
complexity
um
um so but you would need to I think
um at the end of the day write down the
model or what you were trying to
compress
um from you know and from my point of
view your if I was trying to understand
a member of my family another another
you know real sentient artifact
um I I will be reverse engineering their
their model their understanding the
world here how they were compressing
their observations
but when I simulate an agent I'm doing
I'm doing the other thing I'm doing it
in reverse I'm writing down a generative
model and then just using the gradient
flows and the updates on T to t plus one
uh on under the assumption that they are
going to
um minimize their complexity for example
um and this has a name it's called the
ideal Bayesian Observer assumption yeah
so when you go into biology you always
commit to something called the ideal
Basin Observer assumption which is just
that that your belief updating in your
subject simulated or observed
um is going to comply with universal
computation it's going to be Bayes
optimal from the point of view of
Bayesian statistician
um but of course because you've given it
the the generative model which has got
nothing to do with the real world you've
created a probabilistic zombie and as
you say it's probably you know like the
model that you've created they are
supplying that if you like that
objective function of that function to
generate a continuous time the Dynamics
that you're trying to simulate in a real
person in this digital twin for example
um because you you're supplying that
model it's got nothing to do with what
that model actually sees or you know
it's not gonna it's got nothing to do
with the world out there it's just
appropriate for the kinds of inputs and
observation supplied that by that
particular model
um so I think this you know this this
notion is is it's not just if you like
philosophical
um a philosophical nicety or a you know
an interesting thought experimenter I
think it could actually
locations you know when you tell your
synth your digital twin in fact you're a
digital twin uh then they have to do all
sorts of belief updating should they
want to but you said something quite
interesting you said that the digital
twin they're my digital twin and the
computer
they would just carry on observing
and and because the way I read it was
because they had no way of updating and
being able to predict this random
fluctuation in the sky and this Bosch
part of the sky was bright orange for
example
um they wouldn't be able to see it and
you know I'd certainly could go with
that you you can't perceive you can't
see you can't rep represent you can't
compress you can't register anything
that's not part of your internal you
know repertoire your model of the world
so they wouldn't be able to see what was
going on even if the person presenting
the big orange blob in the sky in in
silica or in in you know in the
simulation was able to see what the
agent was seeing is that what you meant
by by you know this dissociation now
between the obser The Observer and the
Observer of the Observer
um I am also wondering a bit so maybe it
was a it's actually a bit different so
um it's it's nice that you think that
there might be actual applications of
such an approach in these scenarios
um let me say where I see a potential
and then let's see if that's also what
you had in mind so I suspect that it
there's a it's a bit different though oh
so
I think one question that you may want
to ask
um at some point is is my language model
is my simulated agent
you know maybe you simulate a bunch of
neurons at some point is somebody at
home
right so you may want to ask have I
created Consciousness that's the way we
typically tend to phrase it I think
um now we usually think well you know
this question is not a question this is
essentially a question of the philosophy
of mind so you would have to somehow
understand what does Consciousness mean
make a theory of that and and then try
to apply it to that specific structure
that's sitting in your computer or so
um whereas if something like like my
Approach is true then there's a level
below and and that's like asking is
there
um if you were that thing
would would this be coherent with what
the simulation shows right so
um and then the answer turns out to be
sometimes no
which also in particular implies that
there's nobody at home in the way that
you would intuitively think for
Consciousness right even though you
didn't say anything about consciousness
but the idea is that
um
so
not being at home here would would be so
so we tend to say like here's something
I can point to something spatially
localized
perhaps a piece of matter or a
particular localized pattern in my
simulation
and it makes sense to ask what's that
thing feeling or what would it be like
to be that thing you know
um in some sense my Approach denies that
it rather says that if you are if you
are you yeah whatever that means then
you are a pattern right
um it will often look as if you were
spatially localized and instantiated
on some small material part of a larger
process like part of a computer
simulation or a piece of matter in the
world as we think of it
but that's not fundamentally the case
and since that's not fundamentally the
case you can have a Divergence between
these two right you will not have a
Divergence it will just be the same
thing when in in the usual situations
like you know in our world we point at
stuff that has high complexity or we run
a simulation with constant laws point at
a persistent pattern there
there being that pattern is the same
like makes the same probability
predictions as we would describe what
happens to that pattern
but what I described as extremely
counter-intuitive you would have a
Divergence of these probabilities
without being able to point at a
mechanistic course of the diversions
so if you just you're the simulator
you're running your simulation you're
changing the laws immediately
then in principle there's nothing for
you that you can misunderstand yeah you
see what the simulation is doing right
it's running according to these laws and
then the others you see what the
simulated being is doing and saying and
claiming to see
you'll see them watch the newspaper and
being surprised suddenly something's
going very weird and then it sometimes
gets used to it after a couple of times
you can perfectly understand that but
when you ask
if I were that thing in the simulation
shortly before the change happens
what
what are the chances of what happens to
me yeah
when these chances
are given by the probabilities of the
old laws
right so
um and that's information theoretic
reason essentially right it's not
um so when I said intuitively this is
something like the simulated being falls
out of the simulation when I don't have
a mechanistic story to tell like
something kicked him and he really fell
out of it in a mechanistic way you know
it was more that the abstract law that
predicts what observers see tells you
that right and it's just a derived
prediction that the first and the third
person perspective typically agree so
that if I'm the simulator and then I see
what my simulator being is experiencing
that's what it will actually experience
so so the diversions is not mechanistic
in the sense it's structural and
surprising in the sense very
counterintuitive
so what you were hinting at I think
was was also for me very interesting to
learn what you do there but it seemed
that you were able to tell a clear story
about what happens in that simulation of
the like say of your family members of
this little agents that have reduced
structure that you want to predict what
how your family members would respond to
treatment you could still say according
to the mechanics mechanism of the
simulation I can understand this kind of
Divergence between the simulated family
members and your actual ones whereas I
think this would be a different
mechanism a different kind of thing
this is that just said to answer your
question does that make sense
um
nearly yeah it's
still uh you know
the counter-intuitive and the magic
aspect of this is is is what's
intriguing me here so this notion of
being knocked out of the Universe
um that I found quite intriguing so are
you saying then that the simulated uh
Observer from its point of view in the
face of some designed or
um large fluctuation which was
completely unpredictable
um so there's no way that that normal
and
um uh sort of Ideal Observer rules
apply there's no way that you can
um call upon
um Universal induction to to probably uh
respond to or make sense of this this
large fluctuation are you saying then
that from the point of view of the
Observer
um that Observer just disappears gets
knocked this uh but what happens to this
poor Observer that's seen something
that's never seen before in its life and
cannot predict and cannot perceive
um
yes so first note the similarity perhaps
to the boltzmann brain problem and the
way that I tried to ex like come back to
the solution is you know proposed here
um somehow there you also say well you
know
um you would expect business on planet
as usual to persist regardless of how
many copies are out there
whereas that will essentially because
you are your state and it's the same
state here as in the copies
so you shouldn't think of us sitting
either here or there right you summon
all of that at once and now this kind of
colorful interpretation also applies to
the simulation yeah you say let's let's
interpret this for the moment it's not
part of my theory but it's interpret
this is the kinds of many words picture
yeah you can think of all possible
worlds one of them is like the world
with laws as it evolves
like in the beginning of the simulation
unchanged forever
another world is the simulated world
with the change of laws like there are
many other possible worlds
um where essentially a copy of the very
same of server state would appear
now the idea is that you are not
actually the thing in the simulation but
you somehow all of these copies at once
it's more like it's just that some of
these instantiations have higher
statistical weight than others
and those that have higher statistical
weight are those with a simpler word
essentially right so that would be a
kind of many worlds picture if you want
of why algorithmic complexity or
probability would apply here
so
um then
it's in this picture you wouldn't really
say that you're kicked out of the
universe it's just like usually you know
you you would think that you're that
thing in that
regular Universe because that regular
Universe has higher weight
and you're not actually the other one in
the more complex Universe the changing
laws
now if you're the simulator and you look
at the assimilation after changing the
laws you will certainly see a simulated
being in some Observer state
I'm not claiming that this is now a
zombie in trauma sense or so no no I
mean you could also think of what it
would be like to be that thing
it's just when you've been that other
thing before
then that would be a very rare place to
end up later right
so
um so it's very weird so maybe you know
when you have the simulation and maybe
you made friends you think emotionally
attached to the simulated being that you
had run running around there like and
you think like oh I want really that
that my friend as well off in the future
I don't want to hurt the simulated being
and so on and suppose you you want this
at the moment before you change the
simulation
right you want that being to be well off
but you also know that the being is very
unhappy when it sees a drastic change
right maybe that's the personality of
the simulated being it wants to be in a
predicted to build environment right
um but you're now forced to change your
laws should you be worried well in some
sense no because with with high
probability your friend will continue to
see regular laws right it just will be
elsewhere
um you'll then see another being one
that has actually seen changed laws and
you may make friends with them
you may be unhappy that that other thing
is unhappy but but you you know um
yeah it's it's a bit
it's it's even less intuitive than than
everettians want to paint the world I
think
but but it's consistent yeah
maybe the many worlds way of thinking
framing it I think having helps yeah I
think yeah yes I'll
have to think about that a bit more I
think I'd have to do that with a
cigarette and
um one
practical Point
um I have um a lot of friends at the
moment in philosophy of Consciousness
um and they are asking
um very much like people talk about the
neuronal current subconsciousness are
there any computational corrects and
Consciousness it strikes me on quite a
difficult position to to address to
address that you know through the lens
of a physicist and one one argument that
has come to the fore interestingly is
can you simulate Consciousness you you
almost implies that you know one way of
looking at the these uh surprising or
counter-intuitive outcomes under the
application of this Universal inductive
approach
um did speak to you know is there
anybody home you know in the simulation
um one interesting thing that's come out
of that is that
um it might matter
I'm just taking
um going back to a theme a conversation
we're having before about
um the generalized synchronization that
ensues when you're in some
um open or non-equiv and steady state in
exchange with your world as it's going
on predictably uh in the right kind of
way
um it it might matter whether you're
doing your simulation on a Von Neumann
architecture as opposed to not in memory
processing or processing memory uh I
think what Jeffrey Hinton refers to as
mortal computation so that the actual
physics of the Observer State and the
Dynamics and the thing that actually has
um the complexity
um is if you like doing the computation
as opposed to simulating the computation
um and reading and writing all the laws
into memory on a Von Neumann
architecture thereby violating if you
like or abandoning Landau was bound on
the you know on the so she disqualified
that for for the viewers and
[Music]
other friends here
um that but that one way of looking at
that sort of
um
um stepwise change in compression or
Universal induction or the movement of a
belief structure
um with each new observation is you have
to raise information to change your mind
and in raising information needs a
particular amount of thermodynamic work
and there's a lower bound on that or an
equivalent uh that is known for physics
but that only applies when the thing
that's changing its mind is the actual
thing itself uh I saw this is what I was
hoping that Jeffrey intermed by mortal
computation that's not what happens in a
van in a simulation machine it's not
what happens
um in uh The Matrix it could be what
happens in a brain in a vat if you're
talking to a good old-fashioned
philosopher but it's not what happens in
The Matrix where you've actually got to
read and write from memory which takes
all as a magnitude more energy just to
bring you know to bring stuff out so I
was just wondering whether you know it
it it's a slightly practical thing but
if you um if you now admit to the
thermodynamic consequences of your
interpretation in a literal sense via
things like vigilinski equality and
Mandel's principle and you ever really
have anybody there even in a simulation
if your simulation is not mortal in the
sense that it's not using a van human
architecture
this is a fascinating question I I
really like this question because it it
kind of opens up the question like what
if you change your model say you make it
probabilistic instead of chromograph
complexity like which features survive
and which change and in particular this
question like to the implementation
important about how you do the the
computation for example
I take it I just discussed it with Kevin
McQueen about IIT and and what they
assume and whatnot like integrated
information Theory
they we had a long discussion because
they seem to insist that the arrangement
and the actual physical realization does
matter whether you know it can call it
think launches or not whereas I thought
intuitively I thought that's that's I
don't believe that right I think it
shouldn't be it should just be about the
the pattern itself
now two things about that the first
thing to say is um the way I formulated
it now
um the pattern like the way you
implement it doesn't matter
um well it's a matter of degree
essentially
um
I come to that perhaps later but but the
second thing to say is that I like the
question that you posed because you may
ask now if that's my conclusion for this
specific model with the bits and so on
what if I change it will will it then be
more dependent on its thermodynamic
realization and so on so this is an
intriguing question I agree
um to say how it's at the moment and the
way I formulated it
there I would say
um in principle every simulation is is
just a depiction of an existing
structure you're not bringing things
into into existence
unless you you intervene somehow so
let's think about a simulation where I I
talk to the simulated being or make some
decisions and some interventions and so
on
and then the complexity of your
simulated being is not just the
complexity of that pattern or yes it is
but
when you ask whether however whether you
know being that thing is the same as
being in our simulation in that world
yeah then you have to take the
complexity of its description given our
words which imply which includes the the
location functions or how do I pick out
that structure from my world right I
have to say where it sits and what kind
of computation you have to do to read it
out of the computer and if that
computation is too complex for example
if the simulation is running a very
encrypted delocalized way then the
readout function might be so much so
complex that
in total
this world with simulation has very low
statistical weight for that being right
and that it's not actually contained in
the simulation
so there's some sort of
um
degree
um to which like how do how you do your
computation you shouldn't make it too
contrived and delocalized and so on
um yeah
that's I think how it how it's at the
moment
are you happy with that professor
friston
yes I am yes so we've been talking for a
long time now so you'll have to stop us
talking about yeah
minutes because that is 10 10 old in on
the stage it's waiting patiently to ask
you both questions so Professor Thurston
are you are you happy and satisfied with
the questions or do you need more time
all
of our favorite issues thank you very
much let me thank you thank you for all
your time and and it was a lot of fun to
talk to you about this so thank you so
much it is it is thank you so much so
we're going to open up the floor quickly
um I have a question but it's not
exactly a question I think both of you I
have addressed it briefly I'm just
having a bone to pick
so um recently there's an article about
Christoph cough losing a 25 years back
on understanding the neurological basis
of Consciousness it seems like even with
the wine on the line Consciousness
remain
you know and ethnic wrapped in the brain
scan so
I just wondered
who do you both perceive the instant
play of Consciousness and the physical
world especially
when it comes to the integrated
information Theory and Global neural and
work placed here with Robinson so Dr
Muller
could a deep understanding of the
physics of the first person perspective
have unraveled this mystery at all
article that you just mentioned I I was
just in Channel
we should do all we can to study the
neural correlates of Consciousness with
all methods of Neuroscience that we have
um it's just from the other side from
from the philosophy side I see many
arguments that there may of like be very
hard problems remaining like there's a
what trauma is called the pretty hard
problem I think that we may solve one
day with Neuroscience the heart problem
I think we'll need neuroscience and
philosophy it will probably need less
physics than the physicists would want
to believe but that's just my personal
guess as like a non-expert
thank you Professor first
what about your thought
about could you send me a link to the
paper afterwards and it sounds very
interesting so yeah yeah I
I want I lost the 25 years
to
David Chalmer yes
this is Christoph is it
yeah it is we share the same hero so
both Kristoff and myself
um have a hero called Sherlock Holmes uh
a great Detective from London is a
fictional character but that's uh that's
one thing we share in common
um and a common friendship with Julia
turnone who was the architect of IIT
integrative information Theory but I
wanted to disagree with Marcus I I think
we will need physicists to solve this
um to be quite honest
um and I think it is in the direction of
universal computation and these
universal laws that basically dissolve
any bright lines between information and
energy that are going to be at you know
the heart of it I also think that
um IAT is certainly on the right track
but it's it's missing something which
Marcus has brought to the table which is
the the fact that you know there's a
difference between the Observer and The
observed and until you think seriously
about the relationship and the
distinction between the Observer and The
observed and the implicit relational
aspects and I use a relationship
relational as a nod to people like Carla
ravelli and relational quantum mechanics
um I I don't think there's going to you
know I I'm not sure you're going to get
a satisfactory answer about
Consciousness there has to be something
fundamental about the Observer the
measurer the inferior and the and the
relationship between that which is being
measured and observed and inferred
before I think we're going to get any
serious uh get seriously close to a
philosophical resolution of the hard
problem that would be my position and if
Marcus wants to push back on on this Pro
physicist I still have physics I
will not attack the physics professional
let's
not so we're gonna move on
by John have you got
you got it you got a question John
no I think I'm I'm out of my league here
I'm Gonna Leave it to people on the
stage
okay thank you John I'm going to quickly
move on we're going to Adam
thank you
um I uh I was wondering about the
connections
uh to the principle of least action
um if I understand what you're saying Dr
Mueller
um
that uh this principle of universal
induction is what's determining is what
stands in for you know physical laws and
the connection that Dr fishnon you're
making to the uh free energy
minimization I understand these things
in a very rudimentary way but somehow I
feel there's a connection to the
principle of least action I wonder if
you uh might comment on that
so so should I start perhaps um because
I you your ideas sound somewhat familiar
um to something I
as a PhD student I wondered about this
as well and what like certainly you
minimize the action to get the laws
Integrations of motion and mechanics
um can you understand this as a kind of
complexity minimization which is the
story you tell from the other direction
of thermodynamics and computation and so
on
um in the end my like intermediate like
results or conclusion was like perhaps
but maybe not that directly as as I
thought so so so the way I like to think
about the the principle of least action
is really in the architecture of the
world somewhat of you need a couple of
steps to get there and one step below is
I think quantum mechanics and and the
path integral
and when you do an approximation of that
which gives you classical physics you
end up that you have to minimize the
action
and once you have something like Quantum
States
there are information theoretic reasons
for understanding where the path
integral comes from for example
and once you're there you can get to the
principles of each action so the way to
direct the place to look would probably
be information theoretic derivations and
underpinnings of quantum theory and and
the path integral but I think a direct
connection with here maybe maybe action
is just complexity
um among like this and that measure not
the other one out of this complexity so
I don't think that can be made that
easily
thank you
um yeah for me that there is a direct
um
um a link with the principle of least
action I mean you know we often say that
the
um the free energy principle is just a
variational principle of at least action
and the action in this instance is just
a path integral or a time interval of
this bound on marginal likelihood or
negative log uh marginal likelihood
um so the free energy principle
everything that that entails
um is a variational principle released
action I'm just thinking about Marcus's
um answer so uh I you we we certainly
use the pathogable formulation in fact
the other most current
um and in fact the original formulations
the three energy principle
um Drew upon the path integral
formulation you'd certainly need to use
that in contemporary applications of the
um of the free energy principle but you
don't need the quantum mechanics but you
do need the probability distribution so
that the way you get the probability
densities into play is by associating
The Continuous internal bulk or of the
or the Observer space states where you
are in some continuous Observer phase
space with a sufficient statistics or
probability distribution so once you do
that you're back in a world of
um which could which can be cast as
Quantum information theory if you if you
um and some people have tried to do this
um but you don't need to do that you can
still work with classical information
but now you've basically got back into
the world of probably probability
densities by associating
um the internal states with a problem
with parameterizing I represent a
probabilistic description of the causes
of your OBS of your observations and if
you do that then you've got you know you
can read the reality principle simply as
a as a variational principle of least
action I I still submit that you know in
the limiting case of
um the information encoded by bitstrings
algorithmically
um where you you can sort of in the
limited case put Delta functions on
things and using the laws of large
numbers I'm thoroughly hope you can get
from that continuous density dynamics
that the free energy principle employs
to Universal induction
um so if if Professor Muller can write
the paper showing that they're effective
at the same things he can then say and
yes this is also a principle of of least
action yes thank you a
wonderful discussion
uh my question is a kind of context
based you know
if you have an observer in the first
person perspective
is there something it is contrasted
against like an experience of State
and they ask that because I think
eventually The Observer and the
experiencer let's say in quotes
are you know information systems they
contain some information and like you
know what professor frisson said The
Observer State face State refers to the
least action principle of from coming
from free energy
so I'm wondering if any one of you both
of you or both of you can talk a little
bit about this kind of what the Observer
is observing
with reference to these kind of
attributes right some kind of
information based and is there a kind of
you know can you think of a kind of a
database kind of metaphor something
relational versus object oriented I just
want you to kind of philosophize because
I think a lot of people in the audience
would love to hear that aspect I want
Marcus to go first
okay I I'm even less of a philosopher
than he is no I'm not sure but
the answer will will certainly depend on
on the framework
and I I feel like I would have to think
about it but let me say what I what I
understood or what I what intuitively
came to my mind when I heard your
question so
um the way I think of the Observer state
is
um just everything that makes up the
Observer at a single moment in time
which is for you perhaps not the chair
over there
but it's also not just your experiences
it's also memories
um including ones that you're not
currently thinking about maybe
also some aspects that you will never
able to even think about consciously in
the future
so
um the point is when the way I
formulated my Approach you you can apply
it and make predictions and try to
understand these Parcels without
answering the question what say for me
and you this Observer State actually is
and how I should interpret it and where
in this state sits you know experience
versus memory or something like that
it's an extremely abstract level it just
says somehow basically it says whatever
this Observer State means as a bit
string
um there's no like dictionary that you
can open it oh this is not the
experience and these zeros and ones are
the memory it's more abstract than that
the meaning of that status in its
relation to other possible bit strengths
and the computability structure
um it's given to you by information
Theory essentially so this is power you
can do a lot with it but it's that
abstract but it also limits the
possibility to answer more concrete
questions including your question I
don't know the answer to it
thank you Marcus Professor Christine
yeah um so in contrast
um the sort of the classical fep of the
person the quantum fep uh formulations
uh would actually commit to the notion
that the Observer State written as all
the inside of something a particle or a
person
um did
um encode
beliefs probabilistic beliefs about what
caused the thing that's being observed
um which means that there is a
thermodynamic or a physical
instantiation and implementation of the
representation and the information as it
were about something and the thing it is
about is what caused the observations of
course you'll never know what caused
your observations but you can have
beliefs and fantasies about those uh
about those and it is um this kind of
representation if you like or
explanation
um to which the complexity minimization
applies that you you have the least
complex the simplest most parsimonious
efficient probabilistic explanation for
the causes of your Sensations so I've
introduced the word sensation because I
mean when we're talking about an
observer State one could actually mean
the state of the internal
um internal aspects or status say of a
brain or a thermostat
um that is responding to the
observations the sensations which would
be the you know the Therma receptor or
the uh you know my eyes and my or my
sensory epithelia so I think there's a
you know there's another delicate set of
questions and answers to be had about
what what what does an observer State
constitute is it the bulk that's on the
inside or is it the bolt that's on the
inside and the observations that are
impressing themselves or represent the
way of some putative World talking to
the Observer I put it like that because
there's an interesting
um talking about sort of uh quantum
physics and trying to get us away from
philosophy
um there's an interesting
um
map between or relationship between
um the
um the thing that separates my brain
from its lived World which are my
sensory my sensory organs my sensory
epithelia my skin my you know my eyes
and the like
um uh and the notion of a holographic
screen in Quantum information Theory
so another way of if you like looking at
this sort of
um the way that the Observer state is
fundamentally separated from what is
being observed is to think that
um think of it in terms of the
separation in my world that would be the
classical world that would be a Markov
blanket that has these sensory
Impressions upon it but in a quantum
physics or Quantum information they're
not not quantum physics the quantum
information theoretic this will be a
holographic screen that divides the bulk
of one system which could be an observer
from another system that is being
observed that they can only talk to each
other by reading and writing from the
screen itself
um and on that view
um one has to ask is the Observer State
the bulk of the Observer or are you
allowed to include usually classical
information on the holographic screen
and if you can or if you can't more
interestingly I've of course anybody you
know we've spent a lot of time talking
about watching my computer simulation
and I noticed that you know
um Marcus's eyes lit up with all the
counter-intuitive exciting implications
once we started talking about me looking
at another Observer but of course if
you've got this holographic principle in
play you'll never really know what's
going on in the thing you're observing
so it's just it will always be as if
because there's a you know all you can
see of your simulated person or indeed
your loved one
um is what is projected onto that
holographic screen you'll never ever get
Beyond it you know you you know the only
way you can communicate sort of a
classical information at least is is is
is through that so it wasn't a good
answer but you know the experience uh I
I'm assuming then is a an attribute of
the inside the bulk on the inside the
observation is the thing that may live
on the Markov blanket or the holographic
screen which is your window on the world
and possibly that world will contain
other observers but that will just be
your fantasy yes thank you uh you know
for both of you to the wonderful
interpretation of that you know I have a
follow-up question for for professor
fristian
because you have in-depth understanding
of the psychological the psychiatric
side of that same thing
so how do you embed the concept of an
observer phase State space stability
uh is there some you would do you see
some kind of link to the psychological
aspect of our interpretation of the
world and ourselves especially our
identity you know I'm just wondering if
you can uh you know take us through that
for a few minutes
thank you
right I feel selfish using a few minutes
I think we've only got 11 minutes left
without very briefly
um that's a great question
um and indeed it is why um we committed
so much time to investing in in the sort
of the physics of sense making and
belief updating simply because in
Psychiatry and psychology it's all about
beliefs and certain psychiatrists when
beliefs are slightly aberrant
um in relation to uh the thing that's
generating the consequences or the
things you have to least uh beliefs
about and I think you're absolutely
right that a a very important aspect of
um my compress representation of the
world
um is the representation of me as an
actor in that world so you don't have to
I mean a thermostat doesn't have to have
a sense of self but if I have to engage
with other observers it's coming back to
this theme which was recurrent in in the
conversation with professor you know
which was observers of observers if I
live in a world that's full of other
observers like me
um then I'm going to have to have a
model of a good regulator like model of
a good representation a compressed
representation of what it is like to be
an observer including myself so I'm
going to have self models those models
are going to be compressed and what
another way of reading the right kind of
compression is having the right priors
if you remember before the
um the statistical view of uh
compressibility is putting the prize in
the right place so you don't have to
move away from them to make to have a
good explanation for what's going on
including me and how I behave in this
situation and how I relate to this other
Observer
um so people do come along with very
very different priors and in a sense you
could possibly read all neurology and
Psychiatry as people presenting with um
buyers that are not quite fit for
purpose in their world
um and very often they're held with
undue Precision or conviction uh which
means that they're
um
they're very difficult to shift so you
know quite literally they are stuck in a
rut but it's a rut of sense making and
self-modeling and Universal induction
um and then you normally end up asking
you know what are the what are the
biophysical ways in which we represent
that um the Precision of or the
commitment to or the confidence in
certain representations or beliefs and
then there's another story about how
that might be um leveraged from the
point of view of farmer and uh and
Psychotherapy with a cybernetic an AI
ecology currently being currently
building in the world today
how do you anticipate that this will
change the subjective observation
experience of the individual
people used to be able to navigate using
Maps
but today rely on smartphones with GPS
technology and younger people may have
lost the skill to navigate using a map
how will this technology impact the
subject the subjective experience of
observing as an amateur and not an
expert on AI um it's some aggression
that I also find really exciting like
what
how will AI change my everyday life and
that of my children in the next five
years 10 years 30 years
um it's it's very hard to make a
concrete prediction like for me
especially I'm not an expert but also
when I try to follow the experts who
also seem to disagree very much I
personally tend to be optimistic so when
you talked about navigation so the fact
is I was very bad at navigating and
finding my way before smartphones
now I'm much better even when I turn it
off because I feel like when I have it
and I make my way for the first time I
see the map and I memorize it I get a
better understanding and then I can do
even better without smartphone so for me
it's kind of a win-win thing it's not
that I got worse with it I got better
with it I like to hope that something
similar will happen with other aspects
of of us and AI that for example we kind
of personalized teachers perhaps but
tell us in our own best ways of
understanding teachers about whatever
you want to know and will have to learn
um so basically I'm personally
optimistic but it's it's not you know
I'm not an expert it's really just just
a personal feeling
I'm
equally optimistic I I don't really
subscribe to these dystopian views
um
um of what might happen if um artificial
intelligence or
or you know our augmented ability to
download certain cognitive capacitors
into the environment to use the sort of
you know the perspective of Andy Clark I
don't really see that you know I have
this more utopian view of things
um I'll just give you one example I do
acknowledge that certain skills will be
lost
um in children uh basic arithmetic for
example but there are other skills that
they're gaining you know I'm too old now
which is why I asked Marcus to to answer
this is as a proper Millennial I imagine
uh but I'm too old and I don't have a
mobile phone I'm too old to use them
because they're too small and I remember
being on the tube
um about 10 years ago when everybody
apart from me was doing sorry the Metro
um the underground train
um the underground yes the underground
uh everybody had their smartphones out
apart from me so I could just watch
everybody else observe everybody else
obvious serving their smartphones now
what really struck me was you know
children who were able to type using
both funds at an incredible speed I mean
almost at the speed of an insect that I
couldn't physically do so yes they will
probably be completely unable to ever
repeat their times table but they had
such magical flu motive fluency with
their thumbs and their ability that was
a new skill which you know uh you
wouldn't have found it 30 years ago but
you certainly won't find in my in my
generation so I'm sure it's all going to
be okay but things will change in in
terms of our competences and the way
that we relate to our our world and our
e-world so I was just uh I'm just going
to go with the uh trained of motion from
prakash's uh series of questions and
um I was just wondering if um the two of
you could touch on
um there are a couple of terms that help
with this uh
observation and it's uh called
metacognition or meta awareness so I was
wondering if um if one of you or both of
you would like to uh to touch upon like
metacognition or meta awareness
um quick example if I was reading uh age
in a book and say
um uh there what happens to some people
is they they keep on reading but they
lose attention
um and they're not processing actually
the content that they're reading
um consciously
um but there are people that uh
apparently are aware of when this
mind-wandering episode occurs and
um the ability uh apparently is men of
awareness and this can be cultivated in
one's life so I was just wondering if
um and it works with memory right
um as well and that's why I I'm really
happy that you brought up not only just
the experience but the memory aspect
um so if if one of you would like to
touch on uh this
will be great and and thank you both
very very much I mean I know nothing
about this huh
perhaps Professor first then
I I know lots about this because I've
got lots of friends who do metacognition
it's a really important and really
important thing I have to say that the
professor will does know a lot about
this because um he was talking about
observing The Observer quite a lot here
exactly
why I thought of it sorry to interrupt
but you are absolutely correct and
that's exactly what triggered the
question within my observation
and I think it's very relevant I mean
I'm aware that we're out of time now but
I think it's an excellent question
um because you know not only do we um we
we there's a whole science of observing
others and observing The Observer and
dadic interactions and and theory of
mind that speaks to things like autism
and the like but of course we are our
own uh Observer and we can observe
ourselves so as soon as you have that
capacity to
um decompose
in some hierarchical way as it's a
hierarchical uh
um theory of mind or
um high order thought Theory approaches
to metacognition
um then not only do you have the
question of you know what's it like to
observe an observer but what happens if
that Observer happens to be made I think
you get into really deep and interesting
questions of a metacognitive sort just
to highlight how important that is you
know a very sense of self I think
um rests upon that medical tip ability
you know a thermostat and one could
argue possibly a B
um and even small pets do not need to
know that they are a scented thing in
order to operate very very efficiently
as uh you know having a basic kind of
sentence and an observation
um but you know when it comes to very
sophisticated creatures like ourselves
that have to engage with other things
that are equally sophisticated it
matters whether you know I can
contextualize and infer whether you
cause that or whether I cause that and I
now need a sense of self in order to
have that exchange and to observe and
observer that's actually observing me I
think at that level you can see how
easily things can go wrong uh you know
if you don't get these um uh if you
don't have the right kind of of self
model and again we come back to the
potential applications to Psychiatry and
you could argue in some instances
neurology well so yeah great question uh
thank you both of you have given a lot
of material for us to chew on for some
time so my question is very simple
as free agents The Observers as free
agents do they have free will
I'd like to know a quick reaction
from both of you yes they have free will
from my point of view absolutely and in
fact from where where Festival has
started
um you know where am I going to look
next I mean you have to select where to
look next if you have to do that
selection it's only you can do that
because you're the only Observer of your
Universe then you have to have free will
I agree yes you have we will so I'm a
compatibilist I like to read Daniel
um written one paper about her
information Theory can understand your
compatibilism perhaps a bit
so long story short yes I think we have
free will
yeah yeah hi thanks this is this is
fantastic um uh the thing that piqued my
interest was when you mentioned
um the emergence of objectivity and I
just it was the interesting turn of
phrase I thought
um and then you went on and you talked
about it as like the convergence of
probabilities I think
um when you're talking about the
sunrises and stuff and and sort of like
that if an observer calculates the
probability and somebody who's observing
that Observer calculates the probability
and they converged and that is in some
sense ability in objectivity
um so I guess or something like that
first of all
did I hear that right
um
and later you went on and said that you
don't assume objectivity but you get it
as a theorem I think is what you said
um so I guess I'm really curious about
that does that
um is there any dependencies there like
does it emerge in time or like in scale
like spatial scale or does it does it
depend on like the amount of information
you know when you get a certain number
of bits you you things converge and is
that a this convergence is that like a
special condition
um or is it like a generic thing and
then it does
are there can do you know are there
could there be special opinions were
they or it diverges and there's like
critical points things go awry and you
don't you don't have objectivity or I'm
just really curious about that whole
thing I'm I'm curious if you can Riff on
that a bit
yes so that's a great question uh thank
you for it so
um the the main mathematical
background of having such a theorem
um has to do with something a bit
different but perhaps more well known
and that's known as Bayesian coherence
so that would describe a situation not
in my Approach but just in the usual way
that we think the world Works where if
two agents that are immersed in say the
same environment and that that holds
different prior beliefs about the world
and now they go along and you know make
more and more observations
and then under some conditions you can
prove that the Prius will essentially
converge
to the correct distributions if you want
or towards each other so the different
versions mathematical formulations of
that known as Bayesian coherence
um also available some versions are in
quantum theory right
um the interpretation of this would
really be just epistemic about knowledge
I say here's a guy with beliefs another
person with beliefs the more they learn
the more they agree and you cannot agree
to disagree ultimately so that's what
what will happen and what I'm doing
um you don't have that available so you
don't have a joint environment into
which you would be fundamentally
actually immersed
still like the the mathematical reason
why I get such a theorem is essentially
the same and then from the usual
formulation you can kind of learn what
what is important there it's not so much
the scale like how large The Observer is
of the matter or the time it's more the
amount of information that they hold
so
um the idea is that you as an observer
um observe this emerging world and
that's
something that that's predicted by this
approach with certain probabilities so
suppose that's the case
then you point at some thing some
structure in your world yeah
um and that evolves in time as well and
that's what allows you to compare
probabilities your probability of how
that thing evolves versus the
probability if you were that thing right
and the probabilities are close
if the information content of the thing
that you're pointed to is large right so
that's essentially again the Criterion
of that not being a probabilistic zombie
so that's what I called earlier so
essentially the information content of
what you're pointing to of the other
Observer must be larger than the
complexity of the probabilistic loss
that governs its uh it's the relevant
features of the world so the more so
it's like asymptotically it's in the
limit the theorem tells you in the limit
of learning infinitely much information
um your and the first your third person
probabilities and that things first
person probabilities will converge
towards each other
just that sounds very much like a sort
of
metacognitive or perhaps uh Bayesian
coherence version of the law of
requisite variety uh where the variety
is just the degrees of freedom available
to hold that information uh in uh
that's
I have to look that up
I don't even know what that is I make
lots of notes here and stuff to read up
for me it's
it's from the same stable of
cyberneticists that did the good
regulator theorem but you know the
subsequently developed into the lower
lower of requisite variety which is just
having enough degrees of freedom in the
thing you're pointing at
um that
um
is commensurate with the the
informational complexity or you know of
the thing that's doing the pointing I
imagine anyway that's that's your job
yeah
I don't want to spend uh West anymore
anybody's time uh
um because I you know
um
that was a great answer it's uh hits you
in the face when you uh certainly uh
model communication so when the thing
you're observing is actually being
generated by another Observer by an IQ
uh them very very quickly this sort of
um requirement that neither of you can
be probabilistic zombies and you
actually have to have to convince that
generalized synchronization uh see I am
the cause of your observations and your
observations that cause them uh of the
cause of my observation are you are the
cause of my observations you get you get
some you know really nice mathematical
image of the ensuing Bayesian coherence
and the convergence on it
um on a um a synchronization manifold uh
to use the jargon of generalized
synchrony uh that it is just that I just
asked professional would this be
um akin to a principle of unitarity and
entanglementing
in quantum physics everything basically
ultimately coheres is that the idea
um maybe it's
it's the opposite in a way we
have Howard Wise Men here visit and talk
about weakness friend in fact where the
whole puzzle comes from unitarity you
have the friend in the box and vigna on
the outside Winger describes the box and
the friend unitarily the friend
describes it as a measurement
so so in a way there you would have a
situation where you specifically don't
have the communication and then you
don't know what to do then you wouldn't
have because since the consistency of
viewpoints and you don't know what to
say so so that goes a bit back to your
earlier comment which I wholeheartedly
agree so as soon as you have
communication between two agents then
this kind of
um gets rid of zombie status right and
um you have to have synchronization
somehow of of your probabilities either
in an epistemic way whether you would
usually interpret it or in my Approach
really as chances of what happens to you
so
see this whole concept of Observer is
very interesting so my own Insight is
that the Observer cannot be modeled
whereas Observer state is I think what
we are talking about but the Observer
itself can not be modeled because of the
very nature of Observer just as for
example The Taste and other things are a
model of reality but you know of course
scientists who may say that it is like
you know the the content of the chemical
action in the brain or something like
that but that is just equivalence you
know as I experience it exists
independently in
that sense like The Observer exists
independently in reality it seems like I
just wanted to get your views but if you
do consider that observers cannot be
modeled and it's not a thing
because if it has a thing given that
would be observed basically that's the
point and uh and it always you know the
moment you try to observe it then the
Observer has gone back you know meaning
like you try to model something and it
has gone prior to that that state
basically so in that sense it forever
remains independent of whatever you try
to do uh so these are some of my
insights and of course we have a totally
different philosophy based on it called
advaitha and other things just for
information so you are very much uh you
know actually modeling
assuming this type of reality it seems
like to me and I'm quite fascinated with
it and they're going to study more in
more detail
okay thank you I should quickly answer
to that I'm probably running out of time
but just briefly so thanks for the
question indeed you're pointing perhaps
a two different things like two aspects
of it one is like difference between our
server States and observer
um this is something that's common not
only to my Approach but also to other
philosophical questions about personal
identity you know in splitting scenarios
in aberrating many worlds and so on you
know the tele Transportation Paradox
where one person becomes two or so turns
out that in these situations you cannot
meaningfully talk about a person and
identity of persons in a way that we
used to in language right
um so that's that's one observation the
other question that you're touching at
is just the distinction between the way
we model things mathematically and what
we think we really are right so my claim
here is in some sense we we're more like
a pattern rather than a piece of matter
but but even when we talk about these
Observer States as some pattern you can
ask am I the pattern or is the pattern
describing what I am or how should I
think of this relation and this
isomorphism and fortunately I'm
ultimately a physicists don't have to
answer because I I cannot I think this
is a deep philosophical Channel or
question
I would guess thank you both of you for
being here today and it has been a
wonderful wonderful discussion and it's
a lot to unpack today Professor
Christine I will send you the link of uh
Kristoff the 25 years the article will
send you after the the podcast so this
is it gentlemen thank you so much and
it's brilliant to have both of you on I
would like to extend the time can
everybody unmute your mind and wish
things before both gentlemen leaving the
stage can you all unmute and say thank
you please
thank
you
yes thanks
a couple of Sherlocks up there thank you
so much
remember to see you all together thanks
for the conversation a lot because that
was wonderful bye-bye have
a good night
[Music]